<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE root SYSTEM "dictionary.dtd">
<root>
<entry>
<word>
śiva </word>


<meaning>
{śivá} mf({ā})n. (according to <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Uṇ">Uṇ.</a> i, 153, fr. √1. {śī}, 'in whom all things lie' 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 perhaps connected with √{śvi}, cf. {śavas}, {śiśvi}) auspicious, propitious, gracious, favourable, benign, kind, benevolent, friendly, dear ({ám} ind. kindly, tenderly) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#RV">RV.</a> &amp;c. &amp;c 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 happy, fortunate <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#BhP">BhP.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 m. happiness, welfare (cf. n.) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#R">R.</a> v, 56, 36 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 liberation, final emancipation <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 'The Auspicious one', N. of the disintegrating or destroying and reproducing deity (who constitutes the third god of the Hindū Trimūrti or Triad, the other two being Brahmā 'the creator' and Vishṇu 'the preserver' 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 in the Veda the only N. of the destroying deity wss Rudra 'the terrible god', but in later times it became usual to give that god the euphemistic N. Śiva 'the auspicious' [just as the Furies were called ? 'the gracious ones'], and to assign him the office of creation and reproduction as well as dissolution 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 in fact the preferential worship of Śiva as developed in the Purāṇas and Epic poems led to his being identified with the Supreme Being by his exclusive worshippers {called "ṣaivas} 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 in his character of destroyer he is sometimes called Kāla 'black', and is then also identified with Time', although his active destroying function is then oftener assigned to his wife under her name Kālī, whose formidable character makes her a general object of propitiation by sacrifices 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 as presiding over reproduction consequent on destruction Śiva's symbol is the Liṅga {q.v.} or Phallus, under which form he is worshipped all over India at the present day 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 again one of his representations is as Ardha-nārī, 'half-female', the other half being male to symbolize the unity of the generative principle [<a href="/html/abbreviations.html#RTL">RTL.</a> 85] 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he has three eyes, one of which is in his forehead, and which are thought to denote his view of the three divisions of time, past, present, and future, while a moon's crescent, above the central eye, marks the measure of time by months, a serpent round his neck the measure by years, and a second necklace of skulls with other serpents about his person, the perpetual revolution of ages, and the successive extinction and generation of the races of mankind: his hair is thickly matted together, and gathered above his forehead into a coil 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 on the top of it he bears the Ganges, the rush of which in its descent from heaven he intercepted by his head that the earth might not be crushed by the weight of the falling stream 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 his throat is dark-blue from the stain of the deadly poison which would have destroyed the world had it not been swallowed by him on its production at the churning of the ocean by the gods for the nectar of immortality 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he holds a {tri-śūla}, or three-pronged trident {also called Pināka} in his hand to denote, as some think, his combination of the three attributes of Creator, Destroyer, and Regenerator 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he also carries a kind of drum, shaped like an hour-glass, called Ḍamaru: his attendants or servants are called Pramatha {qq.vv.} 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 they are regarded as demons or supernatural beings of different kinds, and form various hosts or troops called Gaṇas 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 his wife Durgā [otherwise called Kālī, Pārvatī, Umā, Gaurī, Bhavāṇī &amp;c.] is the chief object of worship with the Śāktas and Tāntrikas, and in this connection he is fond of dancing [see {tāṇḍava}] and wine-drinking  
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he is also worshipped as a great ascetic and is said to have scorched the god of love (Kāma-deva) to ashes by a glance from his central eye, that deity having attempted to inflame him with passion for Pārvatī whilst he was engaged in severe penance 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 in the exercise of his function of Universal Destroyer he is fabled to have burnt up the Universe and all the gods, including Brahmā and Vishṇu, by a similar scorching glance, and to have rubbed the resulting ashes upon his body, whence the use of ashes in his worship, while the use of the Rudrâksha berries originated, it is said, from the legend that Śiva, on his way to destroy the three cities, called Tri-pura, let fall some tears of rage which became converted into these beads: his residence or heaven is Kailāsa, one of the loftiest northern peaks of the Himâlaya 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he has strictly no incarnations like those of Vishṇu, though Vīra-bhadra and the eight Bhairavas and Khaṇḍo-bā &amp;c. {<a href="/html/abbreviations.html#RTL">RTL.</a> 266} are sometimes regarded as forms of him 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 he is especially worshipped at Benares and has even more names than Vishṇu, one thousand and eight being specified in the 69th chapter of the Śiva-Purāṇa and in the 17th chapter of the Anuśāsana-parvan of the Maha-bhārata, some of the most common being Mahā-deva, Śambhu, Śaṃkara, Īśa, Īśvara, Mahêśvara, Hara 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 his sons are Gaṇêśa and Kārttikeya) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#ĀśvŚr">ĀśvŚr.</a> <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#MBh">MBh.</a> <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Kāv">Kāv.</a> &amp;c. <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#RTL">RTL.</a> 73 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a kind of second Siva (with Śaivas), a person who has attained a partic. stage of perfection or emancipation <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#MBh">MBh.</a> <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Sarvad">Sarvad.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 {śiva-liṅga} <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 any god <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a euphemistic N. of a jackal (generally {śivā} f. q.v.) 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 sacred writings <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 (in astron.) N. of the sixth month 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a post for cows (to which they are tied or for them to rub against) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 bdellium <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 the fragrant bark of Feronia Elephantum <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 Marsilia Dentata <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a kind of thorn-apple or = {puṇḍarīka} (the tree) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 quicksilver <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> (cf. {śiva-bīja}) 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a partic. auspicious constellation <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a demon who inflicts diseases <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Hariv">Hariv.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 = {śukra} m. {kāla} m. {vasu} m. <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 the swift antelope <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 rum, spirit distilled from molasses <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 buttermilk <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a ruby <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a peg <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 time <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 N. of a son of Medhâtithi <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#MārkP">MārkP.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of a son of Idhma-jihva <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#BhP">BhP.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of a prince and various authors (also with {dīkṣita}, {bhaṭṭa}, {paṇḍita}, {yajvan}, {sūri} &amp;c.) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Cat">Cat.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of a fraudulent person <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Kathās">Kathās.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 (du.) the god Śiva and his wife <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Kir">Kir.</a> v, 40 <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Pracaṇḍ">Pracaṇḍ.</a> i, 20 (cf. <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Vām">Vām.</a> v, 2, 1) 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 pl. N. of a class of gods in the third Manvantara <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Pur">Pur.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of a class of Brāhmans who have attained a partic. degree of perfection like that of Śiva <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#MBh">MBh.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 ({ā}), f. Śiva's wife (also {śivii}), {śivā} below 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 ({am}), n. welfare, prosperity, bliss ({āya}, {éna} or {ébhis}, 'auspiciously, fortunately, happily, luckily' 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 {śivāya gamyatām}, 'a prosperous journey to you!') <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#RV">RV.</a> &amp;c. &amp;c 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 final emancipation <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 water <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 rock-salt <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 sea-salt <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 a kind of borax <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 iron <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 myrobolan <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 Tabernaemontana Coronaria <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 sandal <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#L">L.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 N. of a Purāṇa (= {śiva-purāṇa} or {śaiva}) <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Cat">Cat.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of the house in which the Pāṇḍavas were to be burnt <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#MārkP">MārkP.</a> 
</meaning>


<meaning>
 of a Varsha in Plaksha-dviipa and in Jambu-dviipa <a href="/html/abbreviations.html#Pur">Pur.</a>
</meaning>


</entry>
</root>
